Do I have it on? Is it on? It's on. Okay.
Thank you. For me, there's a lot of
distrust in digital platforms that are
going on right now. And there's, as you
saw today, and as you already have known,
there's been many people that do bad
things that will really scare people. And
one of the things for me is that your
personal data is just scattered and having
the opportunity to have Utah lead in this
area and to be able to make it that we and
recall that we own our data. The
government doesn't own our data. We own
our data or we should at least. So it's
important to me that we have privacy,
autonomy and with our state having the
consent of the governed I have many
constituents who reach out to me even as
of yesterday telling me a digital ID is
not the way to go. But as you'll hear
today, there's many reasons why we should
go with it. And I have a firm belief that
even before I took office that we have the
right people in the right place here. And
I think our other states need to join us
with this one and making sure that we
don't do like other countries have done
with our data. Senator Collin Moore,
Representative Keller, You got SB260
passed unanimously through the House and
the Senate a couple years after there was
a different digital identity bill which
I've heard there were pitchforks in
committee hearing and it did not come out.
Why are you supporting and championing
SEDI?
I'll start. I've been fortunate to be able
to work on technology policy in the Senate
over the last several years. It started
with data privacy just in the consumer
aspect and recognizing how important that
is. We've since passed a government data
privacy, the first of its kind, which I
think is also important. But in the middle
there, we're also working on social media
bills and social media policy because
government with technology typically is
always, well, government by its nature is
reactionary, which I don't think is
necessarily a bad thing. But in some of
these technology policies, it moves so
fast that we are not in front of this and
we are allowing people to be exploited.
And the way the internet came up was using
data. The way this has been monetized is
using our data. Facebook, Instagram,
Snapchat, Google, any of these services
are free to us because, as we all know,
you are what's being sold. You are the
commodity. and that in and of itself is
scary and that's what we're having to deal
with as social media right now is social
media companies have exploited that to the
detriment of our kids. They're not only
affecting their mental health but they're
causing actual real world harm like we
just heard about and it's terrible and
putting that same type of power into the
government's hands that has even more
control over so many aspects of our lives
is just super scary. and something that we
need to avoid. We need to flip the script
of how this is being developed and what
this actually means. We need to put the
power back into the citizenry, into
people. People are not commodities. And
that is what the digital age has created.
We are all commodities now. And I think
that's one of the fundamental evils of our
day and age is when we commoditize human
life, that's problematic. And if
government is going to do that, that's
even more problematic. And so we needed to
find a way to flip the script. SEDI, the
bill that we passed, is really just the
first fundamental step. It's laying the
foundation for flipping the script and
saying, no, the power is back in the
people. The power is back in the
individual.
If we look back at history, history shows
us that fighting technology advancement is
often a futile effort. Whether you're a
buggy maker, maker trying to put laws to
stop the automobile or trying to fight
industrialization that technology is going
to move forward because there are so many
benefits to society. So we have a choice
to be proactive and influence and control
these standards or we can stick our head
in the sand and say, no, I don't want
this. I don't I want to fight it. And I
choose to try to be part of the solution.
Digital identity is coming. I think we
all, especially everyone in this room
recognizes that. And the only choice is do
we want to influence the standards and the
adoption of this to protect freedom and
individual liberties or will we acquiesce
to efficiency and monetization. There are
bold visions out there for artificial
intelligence. We hear all around us, hey,
the future is agentic AI. We're going to
have all these agents acting on our
behalf, acting on behalf of an entity or
software program.
The security concerns are very real. You
are not going to feel a smart security
person will not allow an agent to take on
a task on their behalf if there is not
trust. And as has been talked about, our
digital trust structure is under constant
attack right now. And in many areas it
fails. So we have got to come up with a
better system for verifiable credentials
for trusting people and eventually
entities if this agentic future has any
chance of making a real impact without
doing incredible harm in our society. I'm
going to go off script here for the rest
of the time.
Utah in my view has been unique compared
to what I've heard actually from many in
the audience and how we work together
between branches of government. We have
CIOs in the audience. We have chief
privacy officers in the audience. We have
legislators in the audience. We have civil
rights groups in the audience and I've
heard them comment of how is Utah able to
do these things it's doing. So I'm going
to ask this to Senator Kullimore. What is
it that Utah is doing differently than
other states and what should they know so
they can go back to their states and
replicate the success we're having across
our government on both sides of the aisle?
Well, you know, we have to put we have to
set aside our trying to be humble here
because there are some things that work
really well here in Utah and we call it
the Utah Way. But the Utah Way really is
just recognizing that we are here as
public servants. We're servants of the
people. And when you approach these types
of policies, you have to have a little bit
of humility to say, I don't know
everything. And that's especially true in
technology, right? Like I fundamentally
believe in certain principles, but I don't
actually know how the technology actually
works, right? And so sometimes you want to
implement a law and we're talking about
very basic things right here, but whether
it's like whatever the type of law is, I
think it's critically important that you
bring in all the stakeholders and who best
than the private sector and academia. And
so whenever we've worked on these
policies, we have good working
relationships between the Senate and the
House. We have good working relationships
between the legislature and the executive
branch, the regulators who are actually
enforcing this or implementing the laws
that we pass. And it's important because
the policy does not actually work if the
implementer just has their own idea and
goes a certain direction. And none of this
actually works because most of the time
people in government don't have the
technical expertise to know what they're
actually talking about. And so we have one
of the shortest sessions, legislative
sessions in the country. It's 45 days,
begins in the middle of January and goes
to about the first weekend of March. And
we are a part-time legislature. That is
becoming less and less a reality. We're
becoming more and more full-time because
really that January to March, that's game
time, but it's happening all year round.
And so we're meeting with stakeholders and
most of the best policy that we pass
involves academia, people who have the
research and the background on their
private sector, people who are actually
developing these technologies or deploying
these technologies or using them within
their business, policymakers, and and the
executive branch. And so I don't think
we've passed any tech technological policy
in the state of Utah without input from
all of them. And sometimes it takes time.
The consumer data privacy bill that we
passed, I think we were the fourth state
in the nation to pass it, but it ran for
three years and we were getting input from
everybody and it gets whittled down. We
passed a digital asset bill that
recognizes what digital assets are. And it
started out as 16 pages even when it when
it was introduced in the session and
because of input it got whittled down and
said no let's boil this down to the
fundamental principles and then build on
that and I think that's what we've done
here with SEDI is we haven't made this I
mean it's policy it's agnostic to what the
technology is and in fact the technology
is not even out there right now that could
be implemented but it's steering the boat
and it's steering the direction of how
that technology is going to be implemented
and so So this is the opposite of being
humble, but using humility to get to these
policy decisions, I think is what helps
drive the advancements that we've seen in
Utah. Chris, I'd love to comment on that.
I think we have been successful as Senator
Kolemore, and he deserves a lot of the
credit for bringing people together, as do
you, and making some policy. But it's
premature to pat ourselves on the back yet
and say that this great. We have some good
policy, but we haven't seen adoption. And
we can't do adoption on our own. We can't
do adoption by just the legislature
passing a policy. Adoption requires
industry to come up with tools and use
cases that are compelling. And also
because Utah is small, to be successful,
we need your help. We need other states to
join together and show that we have enough
of a consortium to get attention from the
big players to say this matters and
privacy and security and individual rights
are important. So while we've had a little
bit of success, we need to replicate that
by having you join us and agreeing on some
key principles and some key standards
where we can move forward together and
have a larger coalition.
Representative Chevrier and Shepard, I'm
actually going to ask you the same
question. You two probably represent some
of the most conservative areas in the
nation in Utah County. And the fact that
this bill is passed unanimously, I think
one is representative of the work done,
but what is it that's different about this
approach that is helping to win over or at
least gain the trust of those that each of
you represent?
– I can go first. So I think this is going
to be off topic for a second, but it's
really on topic. We have a system of
government in Utah that is different from
most other states, and that is the caucus
convention system, which makes it so that
the grassroots are far more involved with
their legislators than they are in most
states. And I think that that's been a
huge factor because both Representative
Shepard and I have been very involved in
the party and in the caucus convention
system. We have built trust in that arena
that allows us to help transfer that trust
to the legislature and to this technology
that we're talking about. So because we
have that opportunity to build trust, I
think that makes it easier for us to help
people understand because they're willing
to listen to us because we have built
trust with them through that system. Does
that make sense? Okay. Okay.
Part of being elected, I had a town hall
and I had experts in this area come and
speak to those who came. And yes, of
course, we use it through the caucus
convention system that we have that allows
us to have a direct report and be held
accountable by delegates. And that is
where you get the biggest pushback. In
honesty, delegates are very engaged aged
and they know issues and you can't hide.
And it's a great, actually a really great
process. And I appreciate that. I
appreciate the accountability. The
delegates and my voters that I have talked
to about this by knocking on the doors,
they want us to leave them alone. They
want to be able to be safe in this
community, not only physically, but also
digitally. And I believe that the
relationships that having served on a
state level in my party and served just
across the entire state and worked in some
national areas. I believe that that does
open the door to when I bring experts to
my district that they're willing to take a
chance and listen. And it has changed the
hearts of some of them to actually listen.
Sometimes we get stuck in our ways and
think that we have the answers and
something is the boogeyman. But honestly,
when you listen and Chris Bramwell has
come to my district along with Timothy
Ruff and when they have when they have
spoken, people in my district have
listened and that's what I really
appreciate. It's the opportunity to bring
these experts as the good senator to my
left here has mentioned to bring these
experts and to trust them. We have to have
trust in the experts and our people that
we represent have to have trust in us.
It's quite the partnership that we have.
Chris, can I add one thing to that? I
think your policy of engaging with critics
has been key to some of the success. There
are some times where in politics where you
don't engage with the critics, you say, I
have a majority. I'm just going to pass
this through. But that hasn't been how the
privacy legislation that Senator Colomore
has helped with or this legislation has
been handled. You've held town halls where
you invited critics to come and poke holes
and things. You've brought in key members
of staff and industry to come and engage
and you slowed down the process to help
convince the critics that this is the
right way forward. And I think that made a
big difference. Thank you. We have six
minutes. I actually I'd like to ask does
anybody have any questions? Any questions
that maybe I
can do it. What is this? The Murray show?
Hi, my name is Sarah Thunberg. I'm the
director of the Colorado Digital Service.
Thank you for having us. We are watching
very closely the work you've done and are
talking about our own legislative agenda
as the legislature, the legislators that
moved a lot of this forward. Do you have
any recommendations for those of us to
take home with us? How we can model
lessons learned, things now in retrospect,
you think maybe we would have done it
differently?
I'm not sure about the done it
differently, but I'll tell you what we've
done that has been working in it. And
Paul, we well, we've all talked a little
bit about it, but Chris has been very
proactive in interacting with the people
who are most likely to be the critics. And
so Lisa and I have been able to set up
these town halls where we can bring Chris
in and have him explain to people. We've
set up meetings with individuals who are
all at night and on weekends, by the way.
Yes, it is out of regular business hours
always. But we've been able to have
discussions with the most vocal critics,
people who have large followings on social
media and we've been able to help them
understand what it is we're actually doing
because the reaction is visceral. I had
somebody on Facebook this morning say to
me that having you endorse digital
identity was not on my bingo card. It
wasn't on mine either, but here I am
because I believe that this is the right
system and I believe that we either have
to choose a system that is going to
respect privacy or we're going to get the
other one. And so we need to make the
choice and we need to make it soon. I'm
going to make a comment too. You need a
champion in your state. When Senator
Kallamore and Moss created the CPO role,
they empowered it to be a champion. You
need every government entity fights for
certain rights for the public. Public
safety is to provide safety. Lands is to
protect the public lands. Health and human
services is to ensure there's public
health and human service. do you have a
privacy or digital identity champion in
your state that is empowered to even fight
for this issue? It's a balancing and
that's part of the governance framework.
So if you don't have that, get it going or
be the champion. I'll just add, you know,
as state legislators, what's awesome about
being in state policy is that you can pass
a bill and then you see the effects of it
like almost immediately. And that's pretty
rewarding. The downside of that is you
want to do everything right now. And
that's just not possible in these types of
bills. We could have said you will
implement these policies and forced it
upon all the government agencies and all
the political subdivisions of the state
and cities and counties and it would have
fell on its face and we would have got
zero adoption because there's no way to
even adopt it right now. We're doing about
that with government data privacy. We
wanted all of the cities, the counties,
the state agencies, our schools and
everything like that to adopt all these
things and you will implement data privacy
right now and you will implement all these
retention policies and you'll get rid of
this stuff. And it's just impractical and
you're setting yourself up for failure.
And so you do have to reel back a little
bit and say, you know what, I'm just gonna
let's just pass this right now and let's
build that. And even as Chris said, you
know, we did a data private or we did the
chief privacy officer a few years ago and
we just keep slowly building on that. And
so you do have to have patience, which is
not always a virtue of state legislators.
– Good morning. I'm Shanna Durant with the
Department of Public Safety. Thanks for
having us. I have a question particularly
for representatives. You say you've had a
lot of town halls. I'm curious about how
often you're having them and how much
you're publicizing them because you say
that we're talking to a lot of people who
are social media influencers. But for
example, Representative Cutler, my parents
are actually some of your neighbors. So
they've never heard about this until I
talked to them. So how much is their
public outreach to more than just social
media and advocacy groups? And what can we
do on our side as public entities as state
entities to assist in that but also give
other solutions to help you with an
enhanced identity and what can we bring to
the table in order to make it better.
Thanks for the question. I think that's
important. So when I mentioned all these
town halls, they were fairly targeted and
the efforts to focus on the policy have
been targeted with those who are probably
the fiercest advocates either for or
against. Let's be honest. Most regular
people, most people, this issue hasn't hit
them yet because there is nothing for them
to adopt. today. Yes, they could adopt our
mobile driver's license, which they may or
may not be able to get through Homeland
Security.
But we don't have a digital identity for
them to adopt yet. So the efforts for
advocacy were targeted at the key
stakeholders, those who are most concerned
about privacy, those who are most
concerned about the technology used. And
the next wave once we have a solution
ready to be adopted would be to go out to
all the citizens and explain how this is
used, how this helps your life, how this
can help verify ages on social media, how
it helps protect their family from online
fraud, which are real pressing problems
that we all recognize and we're all trying
to deal with. And we've got to get to a
point where we have a solution for them.
So we have a policy solution today. We do
not have a market solution until we get
your help to agree on a standard and
products. And I know we're out of time,
but it's a little bit of a catch-22,
right? Because if you go to a town hall,
you've got, you know, I'll publish a town
hall for thousands of people and the same
12 people show up and they're a little bit
older oftentimes and they're not
technologically savvy. and I would bring
up some of these topics and my wife would
be there and she'd be like, you've got to
stop talking about that. They don't care.
It goes over their head and I think you're
just scaring them anyways. So it's a
little bit hard, right? Because you have
to find these focus groups of people who
are like keyed in on this, tuned in. But
to your point, we've got to find a way
that people understand that. I do believe
this is critically important. And as we're
moving into this digital age, if
government does not get out in front of
us, of this, it's going to be a problem.
It's going to undermine democracy. So I
will say the approach for communication
though has been to communicate with every
elected official where a town hall is
being held. So UVU was partnered with for
that. So they emailed every elected
senator, representative, county
commissioner, mayors in every one of the
areas where the town halls were. So it was
very much focused toward who are the
people actually elected to represent the
people. And then they were asked to
communicate it out. The other thing I'll
say though is This approach we're talking
about SEDI doesn't even exist yet. We're
so early in bringing the public in. You
have 29 states already going down a
digital identity path with mobile driver's
license or with W3C credentials or others
in California or Colorado. This is unique
of how early this is happening and people
don't realize the train has already left
the station in some way and we're having
to move the market to try to move
everything in this direction and we're
needing to now come in with new policies
and standards that we need to have all of
that stuff now go back and be compared to
to make sure it can meet them. Let's end
15 seconds. What's your pitch for states
to come and join the consortium? I'll
throw out on this. Many of us recognize
that we let tech
giants and the market determine the
principles by which social media operates
and and is distributed and affects our
families. I think we have a lesson learned
from that that we need to think carefully
about in this AI world, how do we want to
change that or influence how we control
digital identity so we don't have the
mistake of people who are kids accessing
things they shouldn't. So this is a chance
to help solve that problem with youth
identity and to solve the economic problem
of how do I put
Greece in the system to allow economic
transactions with trust to happen across
the world? – I think we need 49 more Chris
Bramwell across the country. That's a
definite statement. And his team. I've
seen the hard work that they do and the
innovation. Utah's famous for being
innovative. And we need the other states
to join us. We can't do this alone. I
think get your states to get a data
privacy expert and an officer, a director,
whatever your role is, all of the above.
And get your teams of the experts in the
field. I'll tell you, I was on a panel
here for synthetic data. I'm just a normal
person just carrying the voice of the
people. And I sat there and every other
person had a PhD. I'm looking at one right
now. And they are incredibly brilliant.
They are the ones that have come up with
the solutions. We're the ones up here that
are helping to implement those across the
country. So we need your help. Are you
going to go? I'll go. Sure. So I have zero
confidence in Congress getting anything
done in this space. I have to the extent
they get anything done, I have less
confidence that it's going to be done
right and not influenced by the big tech
giants that are looking to again
commoditize our data and our people. We
need to get back to the principles of
America that made us great. We are the
laboratories of democracy and if we want
to push this policy, we need a critical
mass of states that align with with these
policies, adopt these principles, and we
will see mass implementation and mass
adoption of these types of principles and
policies because the states are going to
lead out. And that's why you're here. We
need you to help us. We need you to join
with us. And your idea might look just a
little bit different and that's okay. But
if the states are working together and
leading this effort, the interoperability
that people are concerned about will
happen naturally because we're working
together and we don't have to rely on the
federal government nor should we. That's
not how our country was set up. We can
find the solution here and we encourage
you to join us. So I think since I'm last,
this is what I want to say. We have worked
together as a group in our state and we
would like to now extend that out to other
states and start bringing each of you in.
We'll talk to you one-on-one. That's what
we've done here. Anytime there's somebody
who has questions, Chris will go and talk
to them. Now there's only one Chris, so we
can't we can't we don't want to spend him.
But what we can do is help people to
understand this one-on-one. Nobody that
we've talked to that I'm aware of has been
opposed to this once they understood it.
So I think the key is educating people on
what it is we're trying to do and what the
stakes are and the stakes are very high.
So for future generations let's work
together and let's get this done. Thank
you. Let's give them a round of applause.
Max Max Max Max Max Max Max Max Max Max
Max Max Max